Pat Mitchell: What is the story of this pin?
بات ميتشيل : ماهي قصة هذا الدبوس
Madeleine Albright: This is "Breaking the Glass Ceiling."
مادلين آولبريت : انه دبوس كسر الاسقف الزجاجية ( كسر العزلة )
PM: Oh.
بات ميتشيل : آه ,,
That was well chosen, I would say, for TEDWomen.
انه اختيار مناسب اذاً .. لمؤتمر تيد للنساء
MA: Most of the time I spend when I get up in the morning
مادلين آولبريت : غالباً عندما استيقظ في الصباح
is trying to figure out what is going to happen.
احاول ان اتوقع مالذي سيحدث
And none of this pin stuff would have happened
ولا شيء من هذه الامور المتعلقة بالدبوس
if it hadn't been for Saddam Hussein.
كان يمكن ان تحصل لولا صدام حسين
I'll tell you what happened.
سوف اخبركم ماذا حدث
I went to the United Nations as an ambassador,
كنت قد ذهبت الى الامم المتحدة كسفيرة
and it was after the Gulf War,
وذلك بعد حرب الخليج
and I was an instructed ambassador.
وكنت سفيرة موجهه
And the cease-fire had been translated
وكان قرار وقف اطلاق النار قد تحول
into a series of sanctions resolutions,
الى سلسلة عقوبات تفرض على العراق
and my instructions
وكانت تعليماتي
were to say perfectly terrible things about Saddam Hussein constantly,
ان استمر بقول اشياء سيئة فيما يخص صدام حسين
which he deserved -- he had invaded another country.
والتي كان يستحقها .. لانه احتل دولة اخرى
And so all of a sudden, a poem appeared in the papers in Baghdad
وفجأة .. ظهرت في صحف بغداد قصيدة
comparing me to many things,
تقارنني .. مع عدة اشياء
but among them an "unparalleled serpent."
و كان منها الثعبان الملتوي
And so I happened to have a snake pin.
ومن قبيل الصدفة انني كنت ارتدي دبوس الثعبان الملتوي
So I wore it when we talked about Iraq.
لذا كتبت عنه عندما تحدثت عن العراق
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And when I went out to meet the press,
وعندما قابلت الصحافة
they zeroed in, said, "Why are you wearing that snake pin?"
سئلوني " لماذا ترتدين دبوس الثعبان ؟ "
I said, "Because Saddam Hussein compared me to an unparalleled serpent."
قلت لان صدام حسين نعتني مرة بالثعبان الملتوي
And then I thought, well this is fun.
فخطر ببالي ان هذا جيد
So I went out and I bought a lot of pins
ومن ثم ذهبت واشتريت الكثير من هذه الدبابيس
that would, in fact, reflect
والتي في الحقيقة
what I thought we were going to do on any given day.
تعكس ما افكر فيه .. ومايجب القيام به في اي يوم اعتيادي
So that's how it all started.
هكذا بدأت قصة دبوس الثعبان الملتوي
PM: So how large is the collection?
بات ميتشيل : كم كبيرة هي تلك المجموعة
MA: Pretty big.
مادلين آولبريت : كبيرة جداً
It's now traveling.
انها تسافر الآن
At the moment it's in Indianapolis,
في هذه اللحظة هي موجودة في انديانا بولس
but it was at the Smithsonian.
وكانت في سيميثسونيان
And it goes with a book that says, "Read My Pins."
وهي متوافقة مع الكتاب الذي عنوانه " اقرأ دبابيسي "
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
PM: So is this a good idea.
بات ميتشيل : إذا هذه فكرة جيدة
I remember when you were the first woman
اذكر عندما كنت اول أنثى
as Secretary of State,
تتلقد منصب وزيرة الخارجية
and there was a lot of conversation always
وكان هناك الكثير من الكلام حول
about what you were wearing,
ما كنت ترتدينه
how you looked --
وكيف كنت تبدين
the thing that happens to a lot of women,
وهذا الشيء الذي يحدث للكثير من النساء
especially if they're the first in a position.
وخاصة ان كن في مناصب قيادية
So how do you feel about that -- the whole --
سؤالي هو .. كيف تشعرين حيال هذا كله
MA: Well, it's pretty irritating actually
مادلين آولبريت : حسناً .. انه مزعج في الحقيقة
because nobody ever describes what a man is wearing.
لانه لا يوجد من يتحدث عما يرتديه الرجل
But people did pay attention to what clothes I had.
ولكن الكثير من الاشخاص يبدون اهتماماً فيما ارتديه
What was interesting was that,
لم ادري ما هو الامر المثير للفضول في هذا الخصوص
before I went up to New York as U.N. ambassador,
قبل ان اذهب الى نيويورك كمندوبة امم متحدة
I talked to Jeane Kirkpatrick, who'd been ambassador before me,
تحدثت الى جين كيركباتريك والتي كانت مندوباً قبلي
and she said, "You've got to get rid of your professor clothes.
وقالت لي " تخلصي من ملابسك الجدية تلك .
Go out and look like a diplomat."
اظهري كما يظهر الدبلوماسيون "
So that did give me a lot of opportunities to go shopping.
وهذا جعلني اخرج في كثير من الاوقات للتسوق
But still, there were all kinds of questions
ولكن هناك الكثير من الاسئلة كانت تدور في مخيلتي
about -- "did you wear a hat?" "How short was your skirt?"
هل يجب ان ارتدي قبعة .. هل يجب ان ارتدي شيئاً قصيراً
And one of the things --
وهناك شيء ..
if you remember Condoleezza Rice was at some event and she wore boots,
ان تذكرتوا .. كونديليزا رايس .. ذات يوم ارتدت حذاءا غريباً
and she got criticized over that.
وتم نقدها عليه
And no guy ever gets criticized. But that's the least of it.
ولكن لا احد يتم نقده من الرجال على هذا .. وهكذا تجري الامور
PM: It is, for all of us, men and women,
بات ميتشيل : انه من واجبنا .. ذكوراً كنا او اناثاً
finding our ways of defining our roles,
ان نكتشف طرقاً لكي نوضح دورنا في هذه الحياة
and doing them in ways that make a difference in the world
بصورة تعكس تغيراً في هذا العالم نحو الافضل
and shape the future.
في المستقبل
How did you handle that balance
كيف يمكنك ان تحافظي على التوازن
between being the tough diplomatic
بين الدبلوماسية الصعبة
and strong voice of this country
وبين الخطاب السياسي الصارم في هذا البلد
to the rest of the world
تجاه العالم
and also how you felt about yourself
وبين نفسك انت .. وتعبيرك عنها .. ولمستك ودورك
as a mother, a grandmother, nurturing ...
كأم .. كجدة .. كمربية
and so how did you handle that?
كيف يمكنك القيام بهذا ؟
MA: Well the interesting part was I was asked
مادلين آولبريت : الشيء المثير .. انني يوما ما سئلت
what it was like to be the first woman Secretary of State
مارايك في ان تكوني اول انثى تتلقد منصب وزيرة الخارجية
a few minutes after I'd been named.
على الفور بعد تقليدي هذا المنصب
And I said, "Well I've been a woman for 60 years,
فقلت " عن كوني امراة يمكنني ان اجيب فانا كذلك منذ 60 عاماً
but I've only been Secretary of State for a few minutes."
ولكن عن كوني وزيرة خارجية .. فهذا منذ عدة دقائق فحسب .. "
So it evolved.
نحن نتطور ..
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But basically I love being a woman.
ولكن بصورة اساسية .. انا احب كوني أنثى
And so what happened --
حسناً .. ماذا حدث هو
and I think there will probably be some people in the audience
و اعتقد ان البعض من الجمهور
that will identify with this --
يعرفون هذه القصة
I went to my first meeting, first at the U.N.,
عندما ذهبت الى اجتماعي الاول في الامم المتحدة
and that's when this all started,
المكان الذي بدأت فيه قصتي
because that is a very male organization.
انها منظمة ذكورية بحتة
And I'm sitting there -- there are 15 members of the Security Council --
وكنت اجلس هناك .. وكان هناك 15 عضواً من مجلس الامن
so 14 men sat there staring at me,
اي اقصد وجود 14 ذكراً يحدقون فيَّ
and I thought -- well you know how we all are.
فخطر لي .. انتم تعلمون كيف هذا الشعور
You want to get the feeling of the room,
فانت حينها .. تريد ان تندمج
and "do people like me?"
وان يعجب بك الجميع
and "will I really say something intelligent?"
وتتساءل .. هل قلت شيئاً جيداً .. هل قلت شيئاً ذكياً ؟
And all of a sudden I thought, "Well, wait a minute.
ولكن فجأة .. قلت لنفسي .. حسبك
I am sitting behind a sign that says 'The United States,'
انت جالسة خلف اسم الولايات المتحدة الامريكية
and if I don't speak today
وان لم تتحدثي اليوم
then the voice of the United States will not be heard,"
فان صوت الولايات المتحدة الامريكية لن يسمعه أحد ..
and it was the first time that I had that feeling
وكانت تلك المرة الاولى التي شعرت بهذا الشعور
that I had to step out of myself
وكان يتوجب عليَّ ان اتجاوز خوفي .. واخرج خارج دائرة انوثتي
in my normal, reluctant female mode
الاعتيادية التي تتسم بالتردد
and decide that I had to speak on behalf of our country.
وان اقرر ان اتحدث نيابةً عن بلدي
And so that happened more at various times,
وحدث هذا عدة مرات
but I really think that there was a great advantage in many ways
ولكني اجزم ان هناك الكثير من الفوائد على عدة اصعدة
to being a woman.
جاءت من كوني أنثى
I think we are a lot better
اعتقد ان الاناث افضل على
at personal relationships,
منحى الصعيد الشخصي
and then have the capability obviously
واعتقد اننا نملك المقدرة على
of telling it like it is when it's necessary.
قول الامور بحرفيتها دون تمويه عندما يحتاج الامر ذلك
But I have to tell you, I have my youngest granddaughter,
ولكن يجب ان اقول لكم .. ان حفيدتي الصغيرة
when she turned seven last year,
عندما اتمت السابعة من عمرها
said to her mother, my daughter,
قال لوالدتها .. والتي هي إبنتي
"So what's the big deal about Grandma Maddie being Secretary of State?
"ما هو الامر المميز في كون جدتنا مادلين هي وزيرة الخارجية ..
Only girls are Secretary of State."
ان كل وزارء الخارجية هن من الاناث "
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(صفيق)
PM: Because in her lifetime -- MA: That would be so.
بات ميتشيل : لانه في مدى عمرها ..(مادلين آولبريت : كان الامر على هذا النحو )
PM: What a change that is.
بات ميتشيل : ما التغير الذي طال ..
As you travel now all over the world,
على اعتبارك تدورين حول العالم
which you do frequently,
بصورة مستمرة
how do you assess
كما تقدرين
this global narrative around the story of women and girls?
فيما يخص منحى النساء والفتيات حول العالم ؟
Where are we?
اين نحن الآن في هذا الخصوص ؟
MA: I think we're slowly changing,
مادلين آولبريت : اعتقد ان التغير بطيء
but obviously there are whole pockets
ولكن من الواضح ان هناك مناطق
in countries where nothing is different.
كثيرة في دول عدة .. لم يتغير وضعها على الاطلاق
And therefore it means that we have to remember
ولذلك علينا دوما ان نعي وان نضع نصب أعيننا
that, while many of us have had huge opportunities --
اننا جميعاً هنا نملك فرصاً هائلة
and Pat, you have been a real leader in your field --
أنت يا بات .. كنت قائدة حقيقة في مجالك
is that there are a lot of women
وهناك الكثير من النسوة
that are not capable
غير قادرات
of worrying and taking care of themselves
على ان يهتموا بأنفسهن فحسب
and understanding that women have to help other women.
وان يستوعبوا كيفية مساعدة غيرهن
And so what I have felt --
وكان هذا ما شعرت به
and I have looked at this
وتطلعت الى العمل من اجله
from a national security issue --
من خلال قضية الامن القومي
when I was Secretary of State, I decided
عندما كنت وزيرة خارجية .. وقد قررت
that women's issues had to be central to American foreign policy,
ان تكون قضايا المرأة محور سياسة امريكا الخارجية
not just because I'm a feminist,
وليس بسبب اني أدعو للمساواة فحسب
but because I believe that societies are better off
لكن لانني اؤمن ان المجتمع يجب ان يصبح افضل
when women are politically and economically empowered,
وهذا يحدث عندما تكتسب النسوة القوة السياسية والاقتصادية
that values are passed down,
التي تقدر وجودهن في المجتمع
the health situation is better,
وانماء المجال الصحي امر جيد
education is better,
والتعليمي جيد ايضاً
there is greater economic prosperity.
وهناك الرخاء الاقتصادي
So I think that it behooves us --
واعتقد انه حريٌ بنا
those of us that live in various countries
نحن اللاتي نعيش في الدول الحيوية
where we do have economic and political voice --
في الدول التي نملك فيها اصواتٌ سياسية واقتصادي
that we need to help other women.
ان نُساعد النساء الأُخريات
And I really dedicated myself to that,
وانا خصصت نفسي لذلك
both at the U.N. and then as Secretary of State.
سواء عندما كنت في الامم المتحدة او في وزارة الخارجية
PM: And did you get pushback
بات ميتشيل : هل تم صدك من قبل
from making that a central tenant of foreign policy?
احدهم عن قيامك بهذا المنحى في الخارجية الامريكية ؟
MA: From some people.
مادلين آولبريت : من بعض الاشخاص ..
I think that they thought that it was a soft issue.
اعتقد انهم ظنوا انها قضية ليس ذات اهمية
The bottom line that I decided
ولكن لدي اقتناع
was actually women's issues are the hardest issues,
ان قضية المرأة .. هي القضية الاصعب
because they are the ones that have to do with life and death
لان النسوة هن على تماس مباشر مع الموت والحياة
in so many aspects,
بعدة اصعدة
and because, as I said,
وبسبب .. كما قلت
it is really central to the way that we think about things.
ان تلك القضية .. هي محورية في التعبير عن وجهة نظرنا في الاشياء
Now for instance,
على سبيل المثال
some of the wars that took place
اليوم بعض الحروب موجودة
when I was in office,
وعندما كنت على رأس عملي
a lot of them, the women were the main victims of it.
كان الكثير من الضحايا .. كما كنت أرى من النساء
For instance, when I started,
على سبيل المثال .. عندما بدأت
there were wars in the Balkans.
الحروب في البلغان
The women in Bosnia were being raped.
كانت النسوة في البوسنة تتعرض للإغتصاب
We then managed to set up a war crimes tribunal
واستطعنا حينها ان نبدأ بمحاكمة مجرمي الحرب
to deal specifically with those kinds of issues.
لكي نتعامل تحديداً مع تلك القضية
And by the way, one of the things that I did at that stage
وبالمناسبة واحدة من الامور التي قمت بها
was, I had just arrived at the U.N.,
عندما كنت في الامم المتحدة
and when I was there, there were 183 countries in the U.N.
حينها كان هناك 183 دولة في الامم المتحدة
Now there are 192.
واليوم يوجد 192
But it was one of the first times that I didn't have to cook lunch myself.
ولكن كانت الفترة حينها الفترة التي لا اطبخ فيها
So I said to my assistant,
فقلت لمساعدتي
"Invite the other women permanent representatives."
" ادعي الممثلات الدائمات في الامم المتحدة " - ضمن فرق الدول الاعضاء -
And I thought when I'd get to my apartment
وظننت حينها .. انني عندما سأعود الى غرفتي
that there'd be a lot of women there.
سيكون هناك الكثير من الاناث
I get there, and there are six other women, out of 183.
وعندما وصلت هناك كان هناك فحسب 6 نساء من اصل 183 دولة
So the countries that had women representatives
والدول التي كانت تحوي في فريقها انثى تمثلها
were Canada, Kazakhstan, Philippines,
كانت .. كندا .. كازاخستان الفلبين
Trinidad Tobago, Jamaica,
ترينيداد وتوباغو .. جاميكا
Lichtenstein and me.
لينشجتاين .. والولايات المتحدة الامريكية
So being an American, I decided to set up a caucus.
ولانني من امريكا .. قررت أن اُنشأ تجمع
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And so we set it up,
لذا جلسنا
and we called ourselves the G7.
واطلقنا على انفسنا " جي سيفن " G7=7 GIRLS
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
PM: Is that "Girl 7?" MA: Girl 7.
بات ميتشيل : أي الفتيات السبع (مادلين آولبريت : نعم الفتيات السبع)
And we lobbied
مادلين آولبريت : وتحدثنا
on behalf of women's issues.
في خصوص قضايا المرأة
So we managed to get two women judges
واستطعنا ان نحصل على حكمين لصالح المرأة
on this war crimes tribunal.
فيما يخص جرائم الحرب تلك
And then what happened
وما حدث لاحقاً
was that they were able to declare that rape was a weapon of war,
انه تم اعتبار الاغتصاب كأحد اسلحة الحرب
that it was against humanity.
المنافية للإنسانية
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
PM: So when you look around the world
بات ميتشيل : عندما تنظرين الى العالم
and you see that, in many cases --
وترين في عدة امور
certainly in the Western world --
وخاصة في العالم الغربي
women are evolving into more leadership positions,
كيف ان النسوة تتربع على عدة مناصب قيادية
and even other places
وحتى في المناطق الاخرى
some barriers are being brought down,
كيف ان الحواجز تتلاشى امام النساء
but there's still so much violence,
ولكن في نفس الوقت يوجد الكثير من العنف
still so many problems,
والكثير من المشاكل
and yet we hear there are more women
والكثير من الاصوات النسائية المهمشة
at the negotiating tables.
على طاولات الحوار
Now you were at those negotiating tables
وعلى اعتبارك من من يجلسون على طاولات الحوار
when they weren't, when there was maybe you --
حيث لا يوجد .. او ربما يمكن القول
one voice, maybe one or two others.
يوجد صوت واحد او اثنين فحسب للنساء
Do you believe, and can you tell us why,
هل يمكنك ان تخبرينا لماذا تتفائلين
there is going to be a significant shift
بحدوث نقلة نوعية في قضايا المرأة
in things like violence
مثل العنف
and peace and conflict and resolution
والسلام .. او الحروب .. والصراعات .. والنتائج
on a sustainable basis?
على المدى البعيد ؟
MA: Well I do think, when there are more women,
مادلين آولبريت : حسناً انا اعتقد .. انه كلما وجد نساء اكثر على طاولات الحوار
that the tone of the conversation changes,
كلما تغير نسق ذلك الحوار
and also the goals of the conversation change.
والاهداف التي يرنو إليها
But it doesn't mean that the whole world
ولكن لا يعني هذا ان العالم بأكمله
would be a lot better
سوف يغدو أفضل
if it were totally run by women.
ان تقلدت النساء كل مناصب الحكم والسلطة
If you think that, you've forgotten high school.
وان آمنتم بهذا .. فأنتن لم تذهبنَّ .. الى المدرسة الثانوية
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But the bottom line
الخلاصة
is that there is a way,
ان هناك طريقة
when there are more women at the table,
عندما تكون النساء جزء من الحوار
that there's an attempt
هناك محاولة لتنمية
to develop some understanding.
تفاهم معين
So for instance, what I did when I went to Burundi,
على سبيل المثال عندما ذهبت الى بوروندي
we'd got Tutsi and Hutu women together
و جمعنا بين نساء "توتسي" و "هوتو"
to talk about some of the problems
للتحدث عن بعض المشاكل حققنا بعض النتائج فيما يخص القضايا
that had taken place in Rwanda.
التي كانت تحدث في راوندا
And so I think the capability of women
وانا أؤمن بقدرة النساء
to put themselves --
على تمالك أنفسهن في الصعاب
I think we're better about putting ourselves into the other guy's shoes
وانا اعتقد انه من الافضل ان نضع انفسنا موقع الرجال
and having more empathy.
وان نكون اكثر تعاطفاً ..
I think it helps in terms of the support
ودمج السياسة والتعاطف يمكن ان يحدث اكثر
if there are other women in the room.
بوجود نسوة على طاولة القرارات
When I was Secretary of State,
عندما كنت وزيرة الخارجية
there were only 13 other women foreign ministers.
كان هناك فحسب 13 انثى كوزيرات خارجية
And so it was nice when one of them would show up.
وكان من الجميل عندما تشاهد واحدة منهن ترتقي في عملها
For instance, she is now the president of Finland,
على سبيل المثال .. واحدة منهن هي الآن رئيسة فنلندا
but Tarja Halonen was the foreign minister of Finland
و "تاريا هالونين" كانت وزيرة الشؤون الخارجية لفنلندا
and, at a certain stage, head of the European Union.
وفي مرحلة ما رئيسة الاتحاد الاوروبي
And it was really terrific.
وهذا رائعٌ حتماً
Because one of the things I think you'll understand.
ان من الامور التي رأيتها عادة
We went to a meeting,
في الاجتماعات
and the men in my delegation,
عندما كنا نحضرها .. كان الرجال في الوفد
when I would say, "Well I feel we should do something about this,"
عندما قلت " انا اشعر انه يجب القيام بشيء حيال أمرٍ ما ... "
and they'd say, "What do you mean, you feel?"
ردوا علي ب " ماذا تعنين ب أنا أشعر ؟ "
And so then Tarja was sitting across the table from me.
و بوجود "تاريا هالونين" امامي على نفس الطاولة ..
And all of a sudden we were talking about arms control,
عندما كان الحديث عن عملية ضبط الاسلحة
and she said, "Well I feel we should do this."
و قالت حينها " نعم أنا اشعر انه يجب القيام بذلك "
And my male colleagues kind of got it all of a sudden.
استوعب رفاقي الذكور الامر بصورة ما
But I think it really does help
لذا اعتقد انه من الضروري وجود
to have a critical mass of women
حضور نسائي
in a series of foreign policy positions.
في عدة مناصب خارجية سياسية
The other thing that I think is really important:
والامر الاخر الذي اعتقد انه مهم
A lot of national security policy
هو ان الكثير من متعلقات الامن القومي
isn't just about foreign policy,
ليس معتمداً فحسب على السياسة الخارجية
but it's about budgets, military budgets,
بل على الميزانيات .. الميزانيات العسكرية
and how the debts of countries work out.
كيف تخرج الدول نفسها من الازمات الاقتصادية
So if you have women
لذا ان كان هناك " أناثٌ "
in a variety of foreign policy posts,
في عدة مواقع متصلة بالسياسة الخارجية
they can support each other
يمكنهن ان يساندن أنفسهن
when there are budget decisions being made in their own countries.
عندما يتصل الامر بالقرارات والميزانيات المتعلقة بدولهن
PM: So how do we get
بات ميتشيل : حسناً كيف اذا
this balance we're looking for, then, in the world?
يمكننا ان نحصل على التوازن الذي نبحث عنه في هذا العالم ؟
More women's voices at the table?
هل بوجود نساء اكثر على طاولات الحوار ؟
More men who believe
هل بوجود رجالٌ يؤمنون
that the balance is best?
بهذا التوازن الافضل والامثل ؟
MA: Well I think one of the things --
مادلين آولبريت : تكمن احد مقاربات الحلول ..
I'm chairman of the board of an organization
في الحقيقة .. انا عضو رئيس في منظمة
called the National Democratic Institute
تدعى المؤسسة الوطنية الديموقراطية
that works to support women candidates.
والتي تعمل لدعم المرشحات الاناث
I think that we need
سواء في دولتنا
to help in other countries
في الدول الاخرى
to train women
ولتدريب النساء
to be in political office,
كي يكنَّ في المناصب السياسية
to figure out how they can in fact
ولكي يستطيعوا ان يعوا كيف يمكنهنَّ
develop political voices.
ان يعززوا من اصواتهنَّ السياسية
I think we also need to be supportive
وانا اعتقد انه يجب علينا
when businesses are being created
ايضاً فيما يخص الاعمال
and just make sure that women help each other.
ان نحرص على ان تساعد النسوة بعضها البعض
Now I have a saying
وعلي ان اقول
that I feel very strongly about,
انني املك شعوراً قوياً بهذا الخصوص
because I am of a certain age
وخاصة انني الآن بمرحلة عمرية معينة
where, when I started in my career,
حيث عندما بدأت مهنتي
believe it or not, there were other women who criticized me:
صدقوا هذا .. كان هناك بعض النسوة من ينتقدني لذلك
"Why aren't you in the carpool line?"
" لماذا لست بمتجر تسوق كذا ؟ "
or "Aren't your children suffering
" هل يعاني اطفالك بسبب
because you're not there all the time?"
تغيبك عنهم لمدة طويلة ؟ "
And I think we have a tendency to make each other feel guilty.
واعتقد ان النساء فيما بينها تملك رغبة في ان تشعر من حولها بالذنب
In fact, I think "guilt" is every woman's middle name.
اعتقد ان الذنب هو اسم النساء الاوحد
And so I think what needs to happen
واعتقد ان هذا يجب ان ينتهي
is we need to help each other.
لكي نستطيع ان نساعد بعضنا البعض
And my motto is that there's a special place in hell
وشعاري هو .. هناك مكان خاص في جهنم
for women who don't help each other.
لكل أمرأة تتقاعس عن مساعدة إمرأة أُخرى
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
PM: Well Secretary Albright, I guess you'll be going to heaven.
بات ميتشيل : حسناً سعادة الوزيرة .. اعتقد انك ذاهبة الى الجنة لا محالة
Thank you for joining us today.
شكراُ لتواجدك معنا اليوم
MA: Thank you all. Thanks Pat.
مادلين آولبريت : شكراً بات ميتشيل
(Applause)
(تصفيق)